Now, we get to step three.
现在来到第三步
We want the values here in the assumptions to
我们希望 假设一栏的值
change depending on which scenario we choose.
会根据所选的情境而改变
We don't want to hardcore them by selecting only the strong case for revenue growth,
在此 我们不希望只选择收入增长、毛利润率和营业利润率的优势情境
gross margin, and operating margin.
来直接输入到假设中
So, now we're looking for a way to tell Excel to use this cell,
而是希望 Excel 能直接完成这一操作
in this row and this column when the scenario is a strong case scenario,
对于优势情境 Excel 使用该行和该列的这一格
and use the cell in this row and this column when
对于基础情境 Excel 使用该行和该列的另一格
the scenario chosen is a base case and change it to this.
并更新到假设之中
This is where offset can be used,
这里就会用到 offset 函数
and here is what the generic function isn't looking for.
这个通用函数的用法如下
So, it's looking for a reference point,
以指定的引用为参照系
some place to start with,
作为起点
and then it's asking for how many rows do you want me to move over,
然后偏移若干行
and how many columns?
和偏移若干列
Based on that, that is the value I'll return in this particular cell.
并把新引用的值返回到这个单元格
Okay, and so for the rules I want
根据规则
it to be able to move to the right row and give me this value.
我希望它能偏移到指定的行 并返回数值
I'm actually going to go ahead and use the match function to
接下来 我会用 Match 函数
match the row based on the scenario that is chosen here.
根据在此选择的情境来匹配到对应一行的数据
So, that just kind of a criteria that we're using and the scenario,
那就会用到某种标准和情境
and so therefore I'm going to use the match function to narrow
我将利用 Match 函数
down which row I am selecting.
限定我所选的是哪一行数据
For the which row am I selecting this one,
换句话说
this one or this one.
要匹配到我想选的
This one, this one and this one.
是第一行、第二行还是第三行
Then the column I can tell is the one over here,
是左边一列
or the one over here.
还是右边一列
So, I'm going to switch over to this tab here because
我在这一格做标记
you can see that I'm using this reference point.
这是函数中的参照系
So, offset is always looking for a starting point.
Offset 函数始终是从指定的起点开始偏移的
So, that's what you do.
就像这样
So when you're actually plugging in the opposite function,
嵌入 offset 函数时
it's starting a reference.
第一个参数就是参照系 (reference)
Reference is the starting point from which to count the number of rows and columns.
参照系是按照若干行和列进行偏移的起点
So, I want in here,
我希望以这一格为参照系
I want the reference point to be let's say this because I'm talking about revenue growth,
因为目前对应的是收入增长率的数据
so I have this empty cell.
这一格留空
So, I'm going to just use this as my starting point and say okay,
作为偏移的起点
go down to this row and this column.
在这一列 向下偏移到这一行
So, I'm going to show you this.
来看一下具体的函数公式
So, I'm saying okay,
我指定
start with this reference point,
以这一格为参照系和起点
blue border cell here,
也就是这个蓝框的单元格
and match for the row,
用来匹配
match whatever is in.
所输入的条件
So, matched function will return for me the row that I'm looking for,
Match 函数会返回我所查找的范围、行和列
which will be C24 because it's looking for this scenario,
首先是 C24 即所选择的情境
matching it within this lookup array,
匹配到这个查找范围
and saying strong case matches the row one of these three cases,
比如优势情境匹配这三种情境中的第一行
and so it's going to return the value.
接着就是要看返回的值
I'm asking it for an exact match,
比如 我希望是精确匹配
that's why I have the match type to be zero.
那我就会将这里的匹配查询方式设置为 0
So, it's going to say, okay match row is one, and then column.
然后就会看到 匹配的是第一行 而列也会进行匹配
So, now I have the match giving me back row is one,
本例中 Match 函数返回的是第一行
and now for this is the column reference.
然后是列参数
So, I'm saying okay, stay in this column which belongs to H28 and give me this cell.
偏移 0 列保持在 H28 所在这一列 最后返回这个单元格的值
So, if it says base case,
如果是基础情境
match will give me back two because off
Match 会返回第二行
the lookup array it'll give me the second row for the first year,
因为在查找范围当中 我想要的是第二行
or rather for year four.
作为第四年的假设
So, when I again, Control, Alt, Shift,
按下 Control、Alt、Shift 键
it gives me minus five,
返回的值是 -5%
which is this case because right now scenario is selected as base case.
也就是基础情境所对应的这一行数据
If I change it to a strong case,
如果改为优势情境
then it switches to minus three.
返回的值则变为 -3%
So, for this one,
对于这一个值
well it's one column of H28.
是从 H28 偏移一列
So, staying with the same reference point,
那么 在参照系不变的情况下
I'm saying H28 is the reference cell,
也就是说 参照系依然是 H28 这一格时
match it to the same criteria, strong,
同样要匹配情境标准的这一格
the scenario criteria and give me an exact match for that row.
然后精确匹配那一行
Then for column I'm saying,
对于列参数
offset move over one column.
我指定 offset 函数偏移 1 列
That's this column here.
也就是这一列
So, it's going to give me minus three.
返回的值就是 -3%
Let me show you how it changes.
表格里的内容是有交互性的 可以随之变动
So, if I say this is minus four,
如果引用的这一格数据改为 -4%
this value changes to minus four.
返回的值也会变为 -4%
So, that's how offset and match are used.
这就是 Offset 函数和 Match 函数的用法
So, for gross margin,
对于毛利润率
the only difference is I'm using the same offset and match combination,
我依然组合使用 Offset 函数和 Match 函数
but this time I decided to use this empty cell right above gross margin,
不过这次用毛利润率的这个空单元格作为参照系
but in essence it's the same exact principle that I'm saying, okay,
本质上说，原则是一样的
for match row H32,
以 H32 作为参照系开始偏移
match it for me for C24 in this lookup array.
在这个查找范围内匹配 C24 的值
That's what the B33, B35 is.
也就是 B33 到 B35 的查找范围
You can see in the purple colored cells,
即这些紫色字体的单元格
give me an exact match of that row.
精确匹配那一行
So, this gives me back row one, two, or three,
匹配函数会返回第一、第二或第三行
based on whatever is inside this scenario strong scenario here.
当然 这取决于所选择的情境 本例中选择的是优势情境
Give me just the column the first with still within the same column
对于第四年 列参数
as H32 for year four and for year five,
依然保持在 H32 所在列
just move by a column.
对于第五年 只要偏移一列
So again, I'm just going to demonstrate.
我来演示一下这个的交互性
So, if I change this to well,
变动这一格的数据
survey in the strong case,
现在是优势情境
so I'm going to change this to 0.32.
所以把这一格数据改为 0.32
It changes to 32.
假设中也相应变为 0.32
This is set up to be 32 percent to
哎呀 这里的 32%
a percentage but I just wanted to be a value, number value.
百分比格式设置错了 应该是数字格式
So, that is how I repeated it for operating margin and using H36 as a reference point,
对于营业利润率 操作方式相同 也仍然以 H36 为参照系
and we get our assumptions and they are dynamic.
提取到动态交互的假设数据
We're finally ready for step four,
最后是第四步
which is the next video.
我们会在下一个视频进行讲解